So in the last video, we saw how do we sought collections and then went ahead to sort
our own collections, which had custom class objects using comparable and did a good job.
But then at then you found out the disadvantages, which we are going to take care in this
video.
And that is with implementing comparator.
It solves everything that was a problem with comparable.
And I'm just going to change this example only.
So what I'll do is the first change I make is I don't want to write the sorting logic in
the class, which I'm trying to sort right.
I want to create classes which are high on cohesion.
As I told you, that's the indices standard practice, we'll just get rid of this here.
And once we do, we'll also get rid of the sorting logic.
This now remains a cleaner class, it just has to do with laptops, right.
So now, next is what I'll do is I'll create a separate class, see, I'll say sort laptops
by and I implement a different interface here called comparator.
It's in Java or Google and just passing the generic argument, what do you want to sort?
I'll say laptop and then hover on this, say implement the unimplemented methods and
it just has one again, it's a sound type, it's a it's a functional interface, we just
has one abstract method and that is compare and just the difference between compare to
and compare is compare to incompatible takes one argument, this takes two both of them.
And because thanks to generics, this now is laptop, no more instance of needed no more
type class, you need to be just dangerous as well, right, and you're not certain.
So go ahead and write your logic, I'll say return.
Let's call them appropriately, I'll say first and second laptop, it's a first dot,
get your dot compare to still, right, just that you've used comparator doesn't mean
the string starts to use comparator as well, they're still using comparable, you just need
to call its own compared to you're not worried about how the logic is written for sorting
behind the scenes, just leverage it, call it, and I'll say second dot, get, yeah, and
that's all.
No, this is a separate class, doesn't have to do anything with laptop, right, but now
how do you call it here?
Because now it still takes the sort method still takes the list in which you're storing
objects of a type, which have implemented compare and boo, but now laptop is not implementing
comparable anymore, right, how do you sorted by using comparator turns out we have an
overloaded version of sort, which takes two arguments, the first one, the list to be sorted
second by which comparator, I'll say new sort laptops better, right, we're using an overloaded
version of sort.
The first one is the list to be sorted, the second one is the custom comparator that you
worked with, and now let's see, does it still do the same, and does first round eight, then
16, and then the 32 gram version, getting the point here, and turns out even in Java 8.0,
we even have a better way to use the sort, that is, you will see Java 8 syntax, you don't
need to now write collections, you just need to say the list that you want to sort directly
to sort, they introduce the sort method directly on that list, and just pass in your custom
comparator here, that's it looks more better readable than the previous one, right, because
you're just sorting that list and then passing the constant custom comparator, and that
is how this works, and now let's say you decide to sort your laptops on the basis
of name, how you do that, you don't need to change anything here, just class, create a new
class, and just copy paste the code, and say sort laptops by name, right, and just change
the logic, that's it, name, and this is a separate class altogether for sorting, for writing
the logic for sorting laptops by name at a different place, and similarly I've been doing
other parameters, I'll say sort laptops by monoclexural, perfectly fine, and this just changes
the method, that's all you need to do, that's it, so three different classes write on
their own, no more tinkering and manipulating or editing that laptop class at all times
whenever you want to change, and highly cohesive classes, this is high equation, this
is high equation and the laptop also is highly cohesive, and all you have to do is, whatever
you want to use, I'll say sort laptops by manufacturer, let's go ahead and run this, now
the laptop is with the laptop app will should come first, and then let know, right, perfectly
fine, and obviously in a menu driven program, and that's an exciting exercise for you after
this video, and that is you have to create a menu driven program, that is let's say we press
one, and then it sorts the laptops by manufacturer, press two, sort the laptop by name,
press three, sorts the laptop by SSD, sort, enter four, sort the laptop by RAM, right, that
should be a menu driven program, and that will just make it completely flexible and customizable
as well, but that is the edge we get with comparator and how it solves the purpose, right,
and when we would bring, or when you would use lambda syntax, or even inner classes, syntax,
you would not even need to write these classes at first, right, you can just go ahead
and write them on the go on the flight, thanks to inner classes, and Java 8 lambda's, right,
in this video again, we saw comparator and how it served the purpose of sorting in the
most convenient of madness.